Hello and welcome to this series on
learning TypeScript, React and React
Native, entirely from scratch and all the
way to advanced production level
concepts. My name is Vandad and the goal
of this series is very simple. By the
end of it, you should not only
understand how to use React and React
Native with TypeScript, but why things
work, the way they do and how to think
about building real-world applications in
a scalable and maintainable way. I want
to be very clear about something from
the beginning. This series is not about
shortcuts. It's not about copying
snippets or blindly following tutorials.
It's about building a strong mental
model, starting from Typescript
fundamentals, then moving into React on
the web, and finally React Native for
mobile, while using TS consistently
throughout. The reason I'm doing this is
because in my experience, the best way
to truly learn something is to teach it.
So, as I work through these concepts,
I'm going to explain not just what we're
doing, but why we're doing it, what
problems it solves, and what mistakes
people commonly make along the way.
Each video in this series is
intentionally long, around an hour,
because real understanding takes time.
We're going to slow down. We're going to
explore edge cases. We're going to make
mistakes on purpose and fix them. And I
encourage you to pause the video, code
along, and experiment as we go. In this
first video, we're not touching React
yet. Instead, we're starting with
Typescript itself. We're going to answer
some foundational questions.
Why does Typescript exist? What problem
is it actually solving? And how do we
set up a clean, modern TS environment
that we can build on for the rest of the
series? If you're coming from
JavaScript, some of this may feel
familiar, and some of it may feel
uncomfortable at first, and that's
completely normal. Typescript is
designed to surface problems early, and
that can feel annoying before it feels
empowering. But over time, it becomes
one of the most valuable tools you have
as a developer. By the end of this
video, you should have a working
TypeScript setup on your machine, a
clear understanding of what TypeScript
is and is not, and a solid foundation
for everything that follows, especially
when we move into React where TS really
starts to shine. One last thing before
we begin, you do not need to be an
expert to follow along. Basic JavaScript
knowledge is enough. And if something
doesn't make sense immediately, that's
okay. We'll revisit ideas multiple times
throughout the series from different
angles. So with that said, let's start
at the beginning and talk about the
problems TS was created to solve and why
it has become such a critical part of
modern React and React Native
development.
Before we talk about TypeScript, we need
to be very honest about JS or
JavaScript.
JS is an incredibly successful language.
is flexible, it's expressive, and it
allows you to move very fast, especially
at the beginning of a project. And that
flexibility is exactly why so many of us
fall in love with it. But that same
flexibility is also where the problems
begin. JavaScript is a dynamically typed
language which means the language itself
does not enforce what shape your data
has, what types your variables are or
what kind of arguments your functions
expect. Everything is essentially
trusted until runtime and until runtime
is the key phrase here. Let me give you
a simple example. Imagine you write a
function that expects a "user" object and
inside that function you access
something like "user.name".
JavaScript will happily let you do that.
It will not complain. It will not warn
you. It assumes you know what you're
doing. But if somewhere else in your
codebase that function is called with
something that is almost a user but not
quite, your program doesn't fail
immediately. It fails later, possibly in
production, possibly for a user,
possibly in a part of the application
that's very hard to debug. And that is
the core issue. JavaScript errors are
often delayed.
In small scripts, that's not a big deal.
You see the error, you fix it, you move
on. But as applications grow, more
files, more developers, more features,
that delay becomes extremely expensive.
Another common issue is function
arguments. In JavaScript, you can call a
function with too many arguments or too
few arguments or arguments of the wrong
shape and JavaScript will not stop you.
Again, it assumes you know what
you're doing. This means your codebase
has an implicit contract, but that
contract only exists in your head or
maybe in a comment or maybe not at all.
Now, let's talk about refactoring.
Refactoring JavaScript code without
types often feels like walking through a
dark room and hoping you don't hit
anything. You rename a variable, you
move a function, you change the return
type, and hope you didn't break
anything. The only way to know for sure
is to run the application and manually
test every possible path or to rely
heavily on tests.
And tests are important, but tests alone
do not solve this problem.
Tests can tell you something is broken
after you write the code. They cannot
give you continuous real-time feedback
while you're typing. They don't help
your editor understand your code. They
don't help with autocomplete or safe
refactoring or documentation.
Another issue shows up when working in
teams. When multiple developers work on
the same JavaScript codebase, you start
relying on conventions and assumptions.
You assume that a function returns a
certain shape. You assume an object has
a certain property. And as the code
evolves, those assumptions slowly drift
away from reality. This is how bugs are
born. Not because developers are
careless, but because the language
doesn't help enforce shared
understanding.
And finally, there's the issue of scale.
JavaScript scales very well in terms of
what you can build with it, but is does
not scale well in terms of maintaining
correctness as complexity increases. The
more states, branches, and data
transformations you have, the harder it
becomes to reason about what your code
is doing at any given moment. So to be
clear, JavaScript is not bad.
These are not design flaws in the
traditional sense. JavaScript was
designed to be permissive, fast to
write, and accessible. But modern
applications, especially React and React
Native applications, are large,
stateful, and long lived. And they need
stronger guarantees than JavaScript
alone can provide. And this is exactly
the gap that TS was created to fill. not
by replacing JavaScript, but by changing
how it runs, but by adding a layer of
safety, clarity, and early feedback
before your code ever reaches a browser
or a device. So, now that we've clearly
defined the problem, we can talk about
what TypeScript actually is, what it
does, and just as importantly, what it
does not do.
Now that we talked about the problems we
run into with JavaScript at scale, let's
talk about what Typescript actually is.
Because there are a lot of
misunderstandings around this. The first
and most important thing to understand
is this. TypeScript is not a new
runtime. Typescript does not change how
your code executes. It does not add
features to JavaScript engine. and
browsers do not understand TypeScript at
all. TypeScript exists entirely at
development time. What that means is
TypeScript's jobs is to analyze your
code before it runs and tell you whether
what you wrote makes sense according to
the types you described or the types it
can infer. When you write TypeScript,
you're still writing JavaScript. You're
just writing JavaScript with additional
information attached to it. Information
that describes the shape of your data,
the inputs and outputs of your
functions, and the contracts between
different parts of your code. At some
point, TypeScript takes your ".ts" files
and converts them into plain ".js" files.
This process is called compilation or
transpilation. And once that happens,
every trace of TypeScript is gone. There
are no types at runtime. There are no
TypeScript checking happening in the
browser or on the device. What actually
runs is just JavaScript.
This is extremely important to
internalize because it explains both the
power and the limitations of TypeScript.
For example, Typescript cannot prevent a
bug that depends on real runtime data
like a network request returning
unexpected values. If your assumptions
are wrong, TypeScript will trust you. It
cannot magically validate data coming
from the outside world. TypeScript is a
static type system, not a runtime
validator.
A strength is in catching mistakes that
are already visible in your code.
Calling a function incorrectly,
accessing properties that don't exist,
forgetting to handle certain cases, or
passing the wrong shape of data between
components.
Another common misconception is that
TypeScript forces you to write a lot of
types everywhere. In reality, one of
TypeScript's biggest strength is type
inference. In many cases, you don't need
to write types at all. TypeScript can
look at your code and figure out what
types are involved automatically.
Types are not meant to be noise. They're
meant to be signals added where they
increase clarity and removed where they
add no value. It's also important to
understand that TypeScript is not about
making your code more correct in the
logical sense. You can still write code
that compiles perfectly and is
completely wrong. What TypeScript give
you is confidence.
Confidence that when you change
something, the compiler will tell you
what else needs to be updated.
Confidence that when you call a
function, you're using it the way it was
designed to be used. And confidence that
your editor actually understands your
code. In that sense, TypeScript acts
like a very fast, very strict reviewer
that looks at your code every time you
save a file. So to summarize this
section, TypeScript is JavaScript with a
static type system. It runs at compile
time, not at runtime. It adds safety and
clarity, but not magic. and it exists to
help you catch mistakes before your code
ever runs.
With that mental model in place, we can
now look at how Typescript actually
helps us day-to-day through better
tooling, better feedback, and a smoother
development experience.
Now that we understand what TypeScript
is and what it is not, the next question
is why does this actually matter in
practice? Because when people hear
types, they often think about rules,
restrictions, or extra work. But the
real value of Typescript is not types
themselves. It's the feedback you get
while you're writing code. Think of
Typescript as a developer tool, not as a
language feature. One of the biggest
advantages of type safety is early error
detection. Instead of discovering
problems at runtime, maybe in
production, maybe from a user,
TypeScript surfaces those problems
immediately while you're still in your
editor. The feedback loop is incredibly
tight. You write a line of code and
within milliseconds, the compiler or
your editor tells you whether that line
makes sense. This changes how you work.
For example, when you call a function in
JavaScript, you're relying on memory,
documentation, or comments to know how
the function should be used. With
TypeScript, the function itself tells
you. Your editor can show you exactly
what arguments are expected and what the
function returns. This means fewer
context switches. You don't have to jump
between files as often. You don't have
to guess. The information is right
there. Another major benefit is
autocomplete and intellisense.
This might sound like a small thing, but
it's not. When your editor understands
the shape of your data, it can guide you
as you type. It can suggest valid
properties, catches typos instantly, and
prevent entire classes of bugs before
they exist. Over time, this dramatically
reduces cognitive load. You spend less
energy remembering details and more
energy thinking about actual logic and
design.
Type safety also shines when it comes to
refactoring. In a large JavaScript
codebase, refactoring can be stressful.
You change a function signature or
rename a property and you're never quite
sure what you've broken. You rely on
tests, manual testing, or hope. With
Typescript, refactoring becomes much
more mechanical. You make a change and
the compiler tells you everywhere that
change has an impact. It turns
refactoring from a risky activity into a
guided process. This is especially
important in React and React Native
applications where data flows through
many components. Types act as contracts
between those components. When a
contract changes, TypeScript makes sure
both sides are updated.
Another underrated benefit is
self-documenting code. Good Typescript
types often remove the need for a
comments. When you see a function
signature or a components props, you
immediately understand how it's supposed
to be used. This is invaluable, not just
for other developers, but for your
future self. And this is where
Typescript really starts to feel
empowering rather than restrictive.
Instead of guessing whether something is
safe, you know, instead of hoping you
didn't break something, you can verify
it. The compiler becomes a partner in
development, not an obstacle.
Of course, this doesn't mean TypeScript
eliminates all bugs. Logical errors
still exist. Runtime data can still
surprise you, but TypeScript
dramatically reduces the surface area
for mistakes that come from misuse,
misunderstanding, or inconsistent
assumptions.
So, when we talk about type safety,
we're not talking about perfection.
We're talking about leverage.
Typescript gives you leverage over
complexity. It helps your tools
understand your code and it lets you
move faster with more confidence as your
applications grow. And now that we've
seen the value TypeScript provides as a
developer tool, it's time to get
practical and start setting up the
environment that will support us
throughout the rest of the series.
So far, everything we've talked about
has been conceptual. We've talked about
Typescript(TS) as a developer tool, about
early feedback, about catching mistakes
before they reach production. Now, we
need to talk about the environment that
all of this actually runs on. Because
before we can write TypeScript, before
we can run the compilers, before we can
use tools like "npm" or "ts-node", we need
Node.js.
JavaScript was originally designed to
run in the browser. That's it. Node.js
JS is what allows JavaScript to run
outside the browser on your computer on
servers and inside developer tooling.
When you run things like npm, npx,
typescript, build tools, and test
runners, you're not using browser
JavaScript. You're using Node.js. So,
Node.js is a JavaScript runtime built on
top of the V8 engine and absolutely
foundational to modern JavaScript and
TypeScript development. If you're
learning TypeScript, React or React
Native, Node.js JS is not optional. It's
part of the ground you're standing on.
Here's the part that often causes
problems for beginners. There isn't just
one version of Node. There are many
versions, older versions, and
experimental versions. And different
projects expect different node versions.
A project might say this requires Node
version 18. Another might say version
20. If you only have one global node
installation, this quickly becomes
painful.
This is where NVM comes in. NVM stands
for node version manager. NVM lets you
install multiple versions of node,
switch between them easily and match the
node version a project expects. Instead
of fighting your system installation of
node, NVM puts you in control. This is
not an advanced tool. This is a baseline
professional tool. So the correct way to
do this is first install NVM then use
NVM to install Node.js. That way Node is
managed from day one. switching versions
later is trivial and you avoid a whole
class of environment issues. This is
exactly how we're going to do it in this
video.
So in this section, we're going to do
three things. Install NVM, use NVM to
see which Node versions are available,
and install the latest or LTS version of
Node. No TypeScript yet, no React yet,
just setting a solid foundation. You'll
see the term LTS come up a lot. LTS
stands for long-term support and LTS
version of node is stable and widely
supported and is recommended for real
world development. For learning and
professional work, you almost always
want the LTS version, not the newest
experimental releases. That's the
version we're going to install. So in
here, as you can see, we found NVM on
GitHub. Scroll down a little bit until
you get to the installation section.
Copy the curl command and paste it in
your terminal.
After doing this, you should be able to
issue any command that has to do with
NVM, such as just NVM. As you just saw,
you should also be able to list the
available Node versions on your system,
and you can also install the long-term
support version of Node.
Once node is installed on your computer,
you should be able to use the npm
command, which is node package manager
to install TypeScript globally on your
computer with the command npm install -g
typescript as you can see on the screen.
After doing that, you should be able to
use mpxtsc
as you can see on the screen in order to
get the version of the typescript
compiler. So let's go ahead and create a
folder with terminal. I've created a
folder called "learningts" and then I'm
going to open visual studio code.
So the first thing that we're going to
do is create a new terminal and in there
we're going to init or initialize a new
typescript project. As you can see we
then get a tsconfig json file which
we're going to go through a little bit
more in details later but for now just
know that this creates a new typescript
project for us. The next step is to
install three important dependencies for
our project. In this project, we just
want to be able to run our TypeScript
code and have it compile and watch
automatically. So you can see installing
nodemon ts-node and typescript as
developer dependencies.
Then we're going to create a
nodemon.json
and nodemon.json file is going to allow
us then to control how the automatic
compilation is going to work. As we'll
see soon, we create a folder called src
index.ts file in there and write the code
that we want to write. For now, it's not
so important. It's just a console log.
It's very easy. It's just a log to the
output. And then we run npx tsc
uh in order to compile the code and
create a new uh compile js file. In the
nodemonjson file, we're going to write
the file that we're going to watch. So
any changes made to that file are going
to trigger this script that we're
writing in "exec". And as you can see,
we're going to compile the src/index.ts
file. And then we're going to pass it to
ts-node which is then going to run that
code for us in the terminal. And we're
going to go into our package.json
and give a script to uh node. And the
script usually is called dev. You can
also call start, but dev is usually what
we use. H. And this allows us then to
run this command in the terminal and say
npm rundev. And it's going to basically
run nodemon for us using that nodemon
json configuration. As you can see, as
soon as we change the contents of our
index ts file and save the file, then is
automatically going to be run for us.
Again, let's start with the most
important setting in this entire file.
strict true. The single flag turns
TypeScript from a suggestion engine into
an actual safety net. When strict mode
is on, TypeScript will complain earlier,
complain more often, and force you to be
explicit about uncertainty. This can
feel annoying at first, but that
annoyance is exactly what prevents bugs
later. In JavaScript, undefined and null
silently flow through your program. In
strict TypeScript, you're enforced to
acknowledge uncertainty. That means you
handle missing values, you handle
optional data, and you don't
accidentally assume things exist when
they don't. This is one of the biggest
reasons Typescript scales well. You'll
notice that strict actually enables a
bunch of smaller checks under the hood
if you want to play with it yourself.
Things like strict null checks, strict
function types, and strict property
initialization. We're not going to
toggle these individually right now. My
recommendation, especially for learning,
is simple. Leave strict mode on. If
something breaks, that's TypeScript
teaching you something. Next, let's talk
about target. This controls what version
of JavaScript TypeScript outputs.
Remember, TypeScript itself never runs.
It always turns into JavaScript. So,
target answers the question, what kind
of JavaScript should I generate? If you
target something very old like ES5, the
output is very compatible but also more
verbose and harder to read. If you
target something modern like ES2020 or
ES Next, the output is cleaner, smaller,
and closer to what you wrote. For
learning and modern tooling, we're fine
targeting modern JavaScript. Bundlers
and environments can handle it. Now,
let's talk about module. This option
controls how imports and exports are
emitted. JavaScript has had multiple
module systems over time. CommonJS, ES
modules, and others. TypeScript needs to
know which one you're targeting. In
modern TypeScript projects, especially
with React, we generally use ES modules.
This aligns with import export, modern
bundlers, and modern tooling. Now, let's
talk about what tsconfig.json file is
not. This file is not a performance
tuning file, a list of best practices,
or something you tweak constantly. In
most projects, you create it once,
understand the key ideas, and mostly
leave it alone. When people cargo-cult
tsconfig.json files, they usually don't
know what problems they're solving. Let
me quickly call out a few common
mistakes in tsconfig.json file. Number
one is turning strict mode off to
silence errors. This defeats the entire
purpose of TypeScript. Number two,
copying a massive config file without
understanding it. And bigger config
files are usually not equal to better
configs. And last but not least,
assuming TS config affects runtime
behavior. It doesn't. It only affects
compilation and tooling.
This exact same file or a very similar
one will exist in any React project,
React Native projects, backend services,
and shared libraries. The names of the
tools change, but this mental model
stays exactly the same. Uh remember,
TypeScript is not magic. It's just a set
of rules and and tsconfig.json is where
those rules live. So at this point we've
done something important. We've just
written a single line of TypeScript code
but we've set their rules under which
all future code will be written. That's
intentional because good tooling
decisions up front make learning
everything else easier. All right, let's
wrap this up. In this first video, we
didn't try to be clever. We tried to be
correct. We talked about why TypeScript
exists. not as a replacement for
JavaScript, but as a developer tool that
gives us earlier feedback and more
confidence. We talked about Node.js
runtime that all of this tooling depends
on. We installed NVM so we can control
our node versions instead of finding
them. And we looked at tsconfig.json,
which is where we tell TypeScript how
seriously to take correctness. If
there's one idea I want you to walk away
with, it's this. TypeScript is not about
writing more code. It's about making
incorrect code harder to write. Before
watching the next video, I strongly
recommend you to do three things. First,
make sure your environment actually
works. Node is installed through NVM.
You can check your node version and that
you understand where tsconfig.json
lives. Second, open your tsconfig.json
again and read it slowly. You don't need
to understand every option, but you
should recognize what strict mode is,
what target means, and that this file
affects compile time, not runtime. And
third, try to break things on purpose.
Write some code later that typescript
complains about. That discomfort is part
of the learning process. The series is
not about shortcuts. It's about building
correct mental models. Some videos will
feel slower. Some concepts will feel
strict or annoying at first. That's
normal and it's intentional. In the next
video, we'll start writing real
TypeScript. We'll cover some primitive
types, uh perhaps object types, and how
TypeScript actually infers types for
you. This is where things start to
click. If this video helped you, feel
free to subscribe and like, but more
importantly, actually code along. That's
where the learning happens. I'll see you
in the next one.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat.